<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Japanese | zakvdm.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/categories/japanese/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zakvdm.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-03T18:40:12+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://zakvdm.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zak van der Merwe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dirty tricks for writing better Japanese]]></title>
    <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/2012/12/04/dirty-tricks-for-writing-better-japanese/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://zakvdm.org/blog/2012/12/04/dirty-tricks-for-writing-better-japanese</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here's a nifty trick I've been using when writing Japanese emails, etc. Like
so many things, it uses the power of Google and is best explained by example.</p>

<h3>The Example</h3>

<p>Let's say I'm trying to write an email to a Japanese friend who I recently met
up with for the first time in a few years. I want to say something that
roughly translates to:</p>

<blockquote><p>"It was really great to see you recently in Japan. Talking and hanging out
with you just like old times reminded me of what a dear friend you are to me."</p></blockquote>

<p>A bit soppy, but it'll do for an example.</p>

<p>So I take a quick stab at writing this in Japanese not worrying too much about
errors for now:</p>

<blockquote><p>この間、日本で会えてくれて、本当に嬉しかったよ。数年振りでも、相変わらずXちゃんと話ができたり、楽しく遊んだり出来たので、やっぱり、Xちゃんは僕の心に親
しむ友達と思えたよ！</p></blockquote>

<p>Now, I fully expect my Japanese to be filled with grammatical slips and
nonsensical bits (history has shown!). Let's see if we can't improve on my
first attempt.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The <strong>Method</strong></h3>

<p>The trick is to use google's quotation mark search feature. When you put a
term in " ", you are telling Google to match that term <em>exactly</em>. This is
useful, because it means I can take pieces of my Japanese sentence above, and
see how many times that exact phrase has been used before.</p>

<p>Okay, so first example: I'm not sure about the 数年振りでも phrase. Makes sense in
my head, but who knows, right? So here's what I get when I google for that
exact phrase:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2012-12-04-dirty-tricks-for-writing-better-japanese.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>172 million hits! If you google the same thing, you'll probably get a
different result (because Google just kind of fakes these numbers, I think),
but the important thing is I can see my phrase used in context right from the
Google search results page:</p>

<ul>
<li>数年振りでも変わらず</li>
<li>数年振りでも変わらぬ空気</li>
</ul>


<p>So I'm feeling a bit more confident in this phrase. What else? Well, the
Xちゃんは僕の心に親しむ友達と思えたよ is an obvious candidate. There's lots here I'm not sure
about, including the use of は, the 心に親しむ友達 and whether I want to be using 思えた
form of 思う (the use of the potential form of 思う is something I haven't wrapped
my head around yet).</p>

<p>But just googling "Xちゃんは僕の心に親しむ友達と思えたよ" brings back no results (not
surprisingly!). So what you have to do is trim it down to sub phrases. This
gets easier with a bit of practice.</p>

<p>I look up 親しむ in my dictionary (you still need the old toolbox handy!) and I
see that I'm being reckless with my particles. So forgetting about the 心 bit
for now, I google "親しむ友達" and google shows me the results for ”親しい友達" instead.
Neato!</p>

<p><strong>SIDE NOTE:</strong> Most of these results seem to come from facebook pages, but when I google:</p>

<blockquote><p>"親しい友達" -facebook</p></blockquote>

<p>I still get a lot of results. I also get results for "心から親しい友達"</p>

<p>Looking up 思える in the dictionary, it seems like it's actually a different verb
from 思う with a different usage pattern (なるほどね). So now I can google
"親しい友達に思えた" and "親しい友達のように思えた" and since the latter gets a hit, I'm leaning
towards that. I also try 思える instead of 思えた and I get a few more results and
I'm thinking that's probably what I want.</p>

<p>I think that's enough to illustrate the idea. After a bit more googling, I
finally settle on this:</p>

<blockquote><p>この間、日本で会ってくれて、本当に嬉しかったよ。数年振りでも、相変わらずXちゃんと話ができたり、楽しく遊んだりできて、やっぱり、Xちゃんは心から親しい友
達のように思える！</p></blockquote>

<p>Now, this probably still has errors. That's not really the point. The point is
that it has gotten better than my original attempt! This may all seem arduous,
but in reality, it goes quickly once you've got the hang of it. Depending on
how important the writing is, you can spend more or less time doing this.
Plus, it's a good way to learn!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kanji stroke orders in Anki!]]></title>
    <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/2012/11/05/kanji-stroke-order-diagrams/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://zakvdm.org/blog/2012/11/05/kanji-stroke-order-diagrams</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/posts/2012-11-05-kanji-stroke-order-diagrams-1-400.jpg" width="250"></p>

<p>Just a quick note for anyone studying kanji (especially if you're doing a variant of heisig). You can download a font which includes stroke orders <a href="http://www.nihilist.org.uk/">here</a>.</p>

<p>With a simple change to my Anki model, all my kanji cards now include stroke order diagrams. Nice!</p>

<p>If you're curious, here's how I changed the card:</p>

<h3>Back Template</h3>

<p>Include something like:</p>

<p><code>html
&lt;span class="kanji"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
</code></p>

<h3>Styling</h3>

<p>Include the following css:</p>

<p>``` css</p>

<pre><code>.kanji {
  font-family: KanjiStrokeOrders;
  font-size: 150px;
  color: #e56727;
}
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>This is for Anki 2.0 by the way, but you could do something similar with
earlier versions. The only really critical part is setting the font-family to
KanjiStrokeOrders.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Haruki Murakami's short stories - TV People]]></title>
    <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/2012/09/19/haruki-murakamis-short-stories---tv-people/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://zakvdm.org/blog/2012/09/19/haruki-murakamis-short-stories---tv-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm finally getting to the point where I can start to read a bit of Japanese.
That is, I can follow the gist of what I read without constant interruption to
look up words and kanji. Actually, I've been actively resisting using the
dictionary. That's just not how I read English when I was a kid; and that's
not fun and not the way to stay motivated!</p>

<p>I've been reading short stories by Haruki Murakami. I've got two of his short
story collections, <em>Blind Willow, Sleeping Woman</em> and <em>The Elephant Vanishes</em>.
At first I went through and read all the super short stories. Ten pages or
less was my rule. I find that I can get through these in a single sitting.
They're a nice size, but the stories aren't all that satisfying. Usually no
real plot or character development. What do you expect in 10 pages, right?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><em>TV People</em> was the first Murakami story published in the New Yorker. I
usually enjoy me a good New Yorker short story, so I was curious to see what a
Murakami New Yorker story looks like. <em>TV People</em> is more satisfying than the
super short stories I've been reading. There's (a bit of) a plot, and you get
to spend some time with the protagonist. Honestly though, I don't like it. I
don't understand it, is another way to word it. To me this story is just a
vague ennui / apathy metaphor blah blah blah. In reading through these
Murakami stories, the cover of my childhood copy of <em>The Emperor's New
Clothes</em> flashes into my head over and over. Presumably the clever people at
the New Yorker know something that I don't, and there really is a <em>there</em>
there in there somewhere, but beats me if I can find it.</p>

<p>On the upside, Murakami is great for students of Japanese (like me!). It's so
accessible, it can give you a false sense of confidence. I sometimes go
paragraphs and paragraphs knowing every word, feeling really good about my
Japanese. That is, until I pick up a newspaper or even a tricky children's
book. There were a few passages in <em>TV People</em> that I found tricky, but most
of it was straightforward.</p>

<p>Reading Alfred Birnbaum's translation of <em>TV People</em> from the New Yorker, you
really get a sense of how simple the language is. I almost feel as if, in
translating Murakami into English, the translator needs to doll up the prose a
bit to make it feel natural. But hey, I'm the one who thinks everyone's naked
here, so I would say that…</p>

<p>If you're just starting to read Murakami, then there are two kanji you should
know. Murakami <em>loves</em> these kanji!</p>

<h3>訊</h3>

<p>訊く・訊ねる is just a fancy way of writing 聞く・ 尋ねる (kiku and tazuneru). There's
probably some nuance I'm missing here, but anyway, you'll see this character
used over and over so best get used to it.</p>

<h3>眺</h3>

<p>Murakami's characters love to 眺める (nagameru - stare/gaze). This one is
actually a standard use kanji, but I didn't know it until I started reading
Murakami.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Words I should know but don't: pregnant]]></title>
    <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/2011/01/10/words-i-should-know-but-dont-pregnant/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://zakvdm.org/blog/2011/01/10/words-i-should-know-but-dont-pregnant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>No back story, just realised today that I don't know this word. Here goes:</p>

<p><strong>妊娠</strong>(ninshin) - <strong>conception</strong></p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>彼女は妊娠したので、健康のことを考えてタバコをやめた。</li>
<li>妊娠している</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<!-- more -->


<p>That's easy enough, but there seem to be a plenitude of other pregnancy
related vocab:</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>身重(miomo) - pregnant (kanji: body + heavy)</li>
<li>妊娠 - conception, example: 彼女は妊娠したので、健康のことを考えてタバコをやめた。</li>
<li>妊婦 - pregnant woman</li>
<li>みごもる - to become pregnant (with various kanji I don't know)</li>
<li>宿る - to become pregnant (also has other, more commonly used, meanings)</li>
<li>孕む - to conceive / become pregnant</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>The list goes on. Phew! I still don't know which one to use. This has long
been a problem for me with Japanese: the dictionaries just don't get me quite
far enough. I have had the same kinds of problems with "give birth." Just
knowing 生む doesn't mean you can use it right. And looking for an example, I
come across this:</p>

<blockquote><p>彼女に赤ちゃんが生まれる</p>

<p> She is going to have a baby.</p></blockquote>

<p>Which may just be the best way to say "pregnant" after all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[新年の誓い]]></title>
    <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/2011/01/01/resolutions/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://zakvdm.org/blog/2011/01/01/resolutions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/posts/2011-01-01-resolutions.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>I never used to be one for making New Year's resolutions, but last year I made
some and now it's time to be held accountable. I made 2 resolutions:</p>

<ul>
<li>Learn the 常用漢字</li>
<li>Do 100 Project Euler problems</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p>So how did I do? I got through 1098 kanji and up to problem 63 on Project
Euler. So I failed at both. But I don't <em>feel</em> like a failure! I was to a
thousand kanji around June when I realised that I was starting to know almost
every character that I saw reading newspaper articles during my lessons. This
is because I learnt the characters by frequency of use, and the 1000 most
frequently used kanji go a remarkably long way. So I stopped learning new
kanji and worked on vocabulary and reading. The point is, I suppose, that I
got what I wanted from the resolution, even if I didn't know what I wanted
exactly up front. (Project Euler is another story for another blog…)</p>

<hr />

<p>This year, there won't be any Japanese learning resolutions. I figure I'm in
the habit of studying anyway… Instead I am going to try to write a little
every day (be it on this blog or elsewhere). Oddly, I know from experience
that this is something I find hard to do.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Side note:</em> I had a bit of a tricky time finding the Japanese for <strong>New
Year's resolution</strong> for this post title. It can be hard to look up phrases in
a dictionary, so in the end I resorted to <a href="http://translate.%0Agoogle.co.za/translate_t?q=new%20years%20resolution&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;hl=en&amp;t%0Aab=wT#auto%7Cja%7Cnew%20years%20resolution">google translate</a> and got the right answer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
