<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Japanese | The Izakaya]]></title>
  <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/categories/japanese/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zakvdm.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-03T14:33:31+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://zakvdm.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zak van der Merwe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Haruki Murakami's short stories - TV People]]></title>
    <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/2012/09/19/haruki-murakamis-short-stories---tv-people/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://zakvdm.org/blog/2012/09/19/haruki-murakamis-short-stories---tv-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm finally getting to the point where I can start to read a bit of Japanese.
That is, I can follow the gist of what I read without constant interruption to
look up words and kanji. Actually, I've been actively resisting using the
dictionary. That's just not how I read English when I was a kid; and that's
not fun and not the way to stay motivated!</p>

<p>I've been reading short stories by Haruki Murakami. I've got two of his short
story collections, <em>Blind Willow, Sleeping Woman</em> and <em>The Elephant Vanishes</em>.
At first I went through and read all the super short stories. Ten pages or
less was my rule. I find that I can get through these in a single sitting.
They're a nice size, but the stories aren't all that satisfying. Usually no
real plot or character development. What do you expect in 10 pages, right?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><em>TV People</em> was the first Murakami story published in the New Yorker. I
usually enjoy me a good New Yorker short story, so I was curious to see what a
Murakami New Yorker story looks like. <em>TV People</em> is more satisfying than the
super short stories I've been reading. There's (a bit of) a plot, and you get
to spend some time with the protagonist. Honestly though, I don't like it. I
don't understand it, is another way to word it. To me this story is just a
vague ennui / apathy metaphor blah blah blah. In reading through these
Murakami stories, the cover of my childhood copy of <em>The Emperor's New
Clothes</em> flashes into my head over and over. Presumably the clever people at
the New Yorker know something that I don't, and there really is a <em>there</em>
there in there somewhere, but beats me if I can find it.</p>

<p>On the upside, Murakami is great for students of Japanese (like me!). It's so
accessible, it can give you a false sense of confidence. I sometimes go
paragraphs and paragraphs knowing every word, feeling really good about my
Japanese. That is, until I pick up a newspaper or even a tricky children's
book. There were a few passages in <em>TV People</em> that I found tricky, but most
of it was straightforward.</p>

<p>Reading Alfred Birnbaum's translation of <em>TV People</em> from the New Yorker, you
really get a sense of how simple the language is. I almost feel as if, in
translating Murakami into English, the translator needs to doll up the prose a
bit to make it feel natural. But hey, I'm the one who thinks everyone's naked
here, so I would say that…</p>

<p>If you're just starting to read Murakami, then there are two kanji you should
know. Murakami <em>loves</em> these kanji!</p>

<h3>訊</h3>

<p>訊く・訊ねる is just a fancy way of writing 聞く・ 尋ねる (kiku and tazuneru). There's
probably some nuance I'm missing here, but anyway, you'll see this character
used over and over so best get used to it.</p>

<h3>眺</h3>

<p>Murakami's characters love to 眺める (nagameru - stare/gaze). This one is
actually a standard use kanji, but I didn't know it until I started reading
Murakami.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Words I should know but don't: pregnant]]></title>
    <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/2011/01/10/words-i-should-know-but-dont-pregnant/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://zakvdm.org/blog/2011/01/10/words-i-should-know-but-dont-pregnant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>No back story, just realised today that I don't know this word. Here goes:</p>

<p><strong>妊娠</strong>(ninshin) - <strong>conception</strong></p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>彼女は妊娠したので、健康のことを考えてタバコをやめた。</li>
<li>妊娠している</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<!-- more -->


<p>That's easy enough, but there seem to be a plenitude of other pregnancy
related vocab:</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>身重(miomo) - pregnant (kanji: body + heavy)</li>
<li>妊娠 - conception, example: 彼女は妊娠したので、健康のことを考えてタバコをやめた。</li>
<li>妊婦 - pregnant woman</li>
<li>みごもる - to become pregnant (with various kanji I don't know)</li>
<li>宿る - to become pregnant (also has other, more commonly used, meanings)</li>
<li>孕む - to conceive / become pregnant</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>The list goes on. Phew! I still don't know which one to use. This has long
been a problem for me with Japanese: the dictionaries just don't get me quite
far enough. I have had the same kinds of problems with "give birth." Just
knowing 生む doesn't mean you can use it right. And looking for an example, I
come across this:</p>

<blockquote><p>彼女に赤ちゃんが生まれる</p>

<p> She is going to have a baby.</p></blockquote>

<p>Which may just be the best way to say "pregnant" after all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[新年の誓い]]></title>
    <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/2011/01/01/resolutions/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://zakvdm.org/blog/2011/01/01/resolutions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_lecw5iqAsG1qeiyu3.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>I never used to be one for making New Year's resolutions, but last year I made
some and now it's time to be held accountable. I made 2 resolutions:</p>

<ul>
<li>Learn the 常用漢字</li>
<li>Do 100 Project Euler problems</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p>So how did I do? I got through 1098 kanji and up to problem 63 on Project
Euler. So I failed at both. But I don't <em>feel</em> like a failure! I was to a
thousand kanji around June when I realised that I was starting to know almost
every character that I saw reading newspaper articles during my lessons. This
is because I learnt the characters by frequency of use, and the 1000 most
frequently used kanji go a remarkably long way. So I stopped learning new
kanji and worked on vocabulary and reading. The point is, I suppose, that I
got what I wanted from the resolution, even if I didn't know what I wanted
exactly up front. (Project Euler is another story for another blog…)</p>

<hr />

<p>This year, there won't be any Japanese learning resolutions. I figure I'm in
the habit of studying anyway… Instead I am going to try to write a little
every day (be it on this blog or elsewhere). Oddly, I know from experience
that this is something I find hard to do.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Side note:</em> I had a bit of a tricky time finding the Japanese for <strong>New
Year's resolution</strong> for this post title. It can be hard to look up phrases in
a dictionary, so in the end I resorted to <a href="http://translate.%0Agoogle.co.za/translate_t?q=new%20years%20resolution&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;hl=en&amp;t%0Aab=wT#auto%7Cja%7Cnew%20years%20resolution">google translate</a> and got the right answer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[～とは限らない]]></title>
    <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/2010/12/30/grammar-tohakagiranai/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://zakvdm.org/blog/2010/12/30/grammar-tohakagiranai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_le99gmATgM1qeiyu3.jpg" width="250"></p>

<p>This is a handy bit of grammar that means something like "it's not always the
case that ~."</p>

<p>It seems like you use it when you want to point out to someone that a certain
expectation is not certain. For example:</p>

<blockquote><p>あなたは結婚するつもりでも、相手がその気になっている<strong>とは限らない</strong>じゃありませんか</p>

<p>You might be planning to get married, but that doesn't necessarily mean that
your partner will feel the same, right?</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<p>On a side note, I used the Japanese dictionary
<a href="http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/thsrs/17327/m0u/">goo</a> to try and get a
better idea of the specific usage. My Japanese is on the cusp of good enough
to use straight Japanese-Japanese dictionaries. In the meantime, I learn quite
a bit by trying to use them, :).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Film Review: 時をかける少女]]></title>
    <link href="http://zakvdm.org/blog/2010/12/21/film-review-the-girl-who-lept-through-time/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://zakvdm.org/blog/2010/12/21/film-review-the-girl-who-lept-through-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_ldspywDDrl1qeiyu3.jpg" width="250">
I've been trying to watch more Japanese films lately. It's a good way to relax and "study" all at once.</p>

<p>時をかける少女 (rendered in English as <em>The Girl Who Leapt Through Time</em>) was shown at the Cape Town Japanese film festival a few months ago but I missed it. I heard it was good though and so luckily I was able to watch it at home.</p>

<p>It is indeed <em>good!</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The basic plot is simple: a girl learns how to time travel and uses that for her own amusement. Despite this familiar premise, the film keeps you guessing.  In some ways the form of the film begins to mimic the action on screen--scenes are repeated, things are reworked, time is squashed and stretched. Despite its sci-fi premise, most of the film takes place in a high school. I spent 2 years teaching in a Japanese high school, and the film's high school felt alive and familiar (another Japanese film I saw recently, <em>Linda Linda</em>, captured Japanese high schools equally well).</p>

<p>The main character, a girl of about 16, is just lovely. In many ways ordinary, she is headstrong, assertive and supremely likeable. She carries the film along in a whimsy that makes the implausible plausible, or at least <em>fun</em>.</p>

<p>At some point the time travel plot unravels (as they all must) and I found myself wishing the ending had come sooner (there were many melancholy moments that felt like endings of sorts). <em>Good</em> flick though. Recommended.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
